howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is joshua bach he is vice
president of research at the ai
foundation
he's previously been a research
scientist at mit and harvard
he is author of the book principles of
synthetic intelligence
psy that's psi an architecture of
motivated cognition
and he has published many papers i also
have to
add this he has one of the most
interesting
tweet streams that i follow you can
follow him
at plinz p-l-i-n-z
and only some of it has anything much
directly to do with artificial
intelligence or cognitive science but it
sure
is entertaining he's certainly in my top
handful
of tweet streams that i enjoy following
so let's start
with understanding sort of your
motivation how did you get into this
and here's a quote from i think from one
of your talks maybe it's from a paper i
don't remember
you said we need to understand the
nature of a.i
to understand who we are
yeah i think that artificial
intelligence is an idea is
in some sense the missing link between
philosophy and mathematics
it's the attempt to make the execution
of processes that allow us to use
language
and make it refer to meaning automatic
and understandable and scalable
and this basically allows us to ground
our
use of languages that have meaning in
machinery that we understand in a
mechanical universe
this idea that the universe is
mechanical might sound limiting to many
people but it's not a very limiting idea
it simply means
that the universe is not magic that it's
not built over
um symbolic correlations or symbolic
causation
but over uh things that have no
conspiracy inside of them
and the other thing is that if you think
of yourself
as a system that has no conspiracy
inside of it
what kind of system is it and ai is the
attempt to build a testable theory of
what that is
and if we are able to test that theory
successfully we will have built a system
that in the ways in which it matters is
going to be like us
which means it's going to be a system
that is able to reflect on its
environment and its own role in it
and make a model of that understand that
and understand its own nature as well
right so this project of
artificial intelligence in my view is
something like
a capstone of the certain philosophical
tradition or maybe of all philosophical
traditions of
the question of what are we in this
universe and what's our relationship to
the universe
that contains us what is the observer
all the other questions come from that
and so it's in my view the most
important question there is
yeah i have to agree that as i've gotten
into
artificial intelligence particularly
artificial general intelligence over the
last
about six years i've started digging to
it in some depth
i've found myself being forced to ask
just those kinds of questions
which kind of surprised me right and of
course we both know that not everybody
interested in ai
is interested in it at this kind of a
level there's an awful lot of narrow ai
these days which we'll talk about later
the distinction between
you know cognitive ai and narrow ai and
artificial general intelligence
and and more applied things so i take it
that you would consider yourself
not just an ai guy but also interested
in artificial
general intelligence i think that
artificial intelligence is an attempt to
reboot the original idea of artificial
intelligence so it's basically
agi and the original ai are the same
thing
when ai started out as a field it was
done by a number of people
across disciplines there were some
cyberneticians there were running
computer scientists computer science was
just getting started
uh some information theorists and even
psychologists
involved in the whole thing and the idea
was
we now understand how computers work we
understand that
everything that we understand we can
express
as constructive mathematical paradigm
constructive mathematics is the part of
math that works and it happens to be
the same as computation so let's go and
teach the computers how to think and
the first generation of people that set
out to do this
were very optimistic they basically
thought this is going to be
an extended summer project maybe a
couple years then we will have make
made tremendous progress and as it
turned out
they did make tremendous progress with
hindsight so they did
a lot of amazing feeds like it didn't
take that long to teach computers how to
play
decent chess which means chess that is
much better than make
abilities even before computers became
superhuman chess
and how to get this thing to do very
simple language understanding
simple planning and so on this didn't
take long
a set of programming languages that we
used today almost all of them have been
invented in their structure and
principles in the first
couple decades after ai has started and
the effort was
very much connected throughout computer
science so in some sense
almost everything that didn't work in
computer science was ai
and when it worked then it became
something boring
and ai has in some sense has been always
the pioneer battalion of computer
science and
very very productive as a field but most
of the people that work on it realize
that
this optimism of building a machine that
thinks in
a short time that is for instance within
the time of a couple grand proposals or
even
your entire career that's very daunting
it's probably not going to succeed
so they're focused on things that uh
were going to give results within the
duration of a grant proposal or within
the duration of a career
and these also the things that were
going to give you tenure so
aia became more and more applied more
narrow and it was about
improving the automation of statistics
and uh developing mathematics around
that and theory around that and so on
and it uh this philosophical project
itself
has only captured the attention of
relatively few people in the field
as philosophical projects happen to do i
think in some sense that's
correct and it's the right thing to do
because philosophical projects are
daunting hard risky and often have only
marginal benefits so
why not go for this thing that gives
very tangible benefits
right here right now and this is what
the majority of the field did
there are also some political upheavals
within the field that happened right
when minsky
claimed that cognitive ai was in some
sense the same thing as symbolic ai i
think he made the wrong bet
and minsky was somebody who was an
extreme visionary
but he was also somebody who wasn't not
so interested in the visions of other
people
and so he's basically screamed at people
that did cybernetics and that
did neural networks and actively delayed
the
development of the dynamical systems
models of cognition and of machine
learning systems
for more than a decade basically who
moved the funding for
neural networks and apparently also
impaired the funding of cybernetics and
contributed to the ending of
cybernetics as a field in the us to get
more
i say suspect funding and airtime for
his own approaches
and in some sense it's not his fault
that he could not see that he was not
right
that his approaches ultimately would
lead to difficulties
in grounding concepts and building an
understanding that goes beyond symbolic
systems
but he inadvertently created a division
between
cognitive ai that was his own followers
and disciples and everybody else
and so the other people did not read prg
anymore and they did not think about
psychology very much anymore
and this division within artificial
intelligence between
people that think about cognition and
psychology and people that
think about how to for instance process
images and that
how to interact with an environment uh
this division
lasts until today in many ways even
though it's
the gap is closing more and more yeah
and and yet
if you talk to people even at google
they will admit
late in the afternoon or after several
beers that the reason they got into the
field was something like agi
absolutely when i entered university i i
only did this because i wanted to
understand how the mind works and that's
why i studied computer science and
philosophy
and a few other things and it was very
disappointing to me to see that
philosophers were completely not
into this mostly didn't understand the
ideas that computer science
has said developed during the last 50
years at all
and if so then only in a very
superficial and derisive way
and the computer scientists were not
interested in philosophy
and it was really depressing to me and
uh i was not alone in this so
when i was a grad student or not even
grad students who basically
post the equivalent of a bachelor other
students would ask me when they entered
the field and there was a tutor
where can i do ai here who's offering
real ai classes
even though we had a very large and
active ai department or university
and so i decided that i had to offer ai
classes right so as a student i started
uh doing a seminar on building cognitive
architectures
and on thinking about the mind and so i
got a dozen students who started
building things with me and this is the
origin
of the microsci architecture by the way
this is how i got
into working in academia as a student
ah that's a very interesting story you
sort of reacted against
the prevailing trends in academia where
as you said earlier
unfortunately the funding and
promotional carrots you know
rewards are focused on you know
relatively small
incremental steps against you know known
benchmarks you know you raise the
benchmark by
half a percent and you have a paper you
can publish when you publish seven
papers you get tenure right
and that's not the grand question of how
do we make a machine
that thinks sort of like a human are you
still optimistic that we can create
computer intelligences that are at human
level and beyond
of course i there is no obvious reason
why we shouldn't
there's nothing magic going on as far as
we know in the brain
i also don't think that there are and
this might be very controversial to some
deep open philosophical questions left
that have to be answered what's what
needs to be answered is
a lot of technical details and
for a lot of these details i think doors
have opened
to work on them in the last few years so
uh even though i don't know how long
it's going to take
and whether it's going to happen in our
lifetime i think there's a significant
probability
that we will see something that is not
human-like but in many areas
superhuman-like and then other areas
good enough like uh within our lifetime
or maybe even in the next few years
yeah it's hard to say you know it's one
of these damn questions it could be five
years it could be a hundred years or
more right and of course it also as you
say
depends on where you're measuring if you
talk about every single facility it
might be 100 years but
if we're talking about superhuman
capability in certain domains that could
happen
or frankly already has happened in
narrow domains like image recognition
under certain very constrained cases and
those windows will
open larger and larger and i will also
say that one of the things that's made
me more optimistic about superhuman
capacity across the board is the more
i've learned about cognitive science and
cognitive neuroscience
frankly how limited the human brain is
things like working memory size
fidelity of memory you know etc
we're not that smart compared to what we
could be working memory alone
is a huge bottleneck on for instance the
practical level of recursion
in language and chunking size of
concepts etc
you know the low fidelity of our memory
and lack of persistence is certainly a
major cognitive limitation
so i'm not one of those people who
thinks that the humans are the top
of the intelligence spectrum frankly i
believe we're
approximately the stupidest possible
general intelligence which is not
surprising you know evolution is
seldom profligate with its gifts and
since we're
over line of general intelligence at
least so it appears
we're probably just over the line and so
i'm
one of those who is also very hopeful
that we can get not just
over the line but way over the line at
least in some very interesting
dimensions
you know such as language understanding
the ability to read the literature of a
discipline and actually make sense of it
etc i remember that i've always been
very disappointed in the capacity of my
brain as a child and
later on and i also felt bad about this
because at the same time i was
confronted with
the superstitious belief of most people
that if you apply yourself there is
basically no limit to what the brain can
do right
we could have maybe infinite memory
maybe if we would just pay attention all
the time
we could read all the books and retain
all the books we could retain all the
movie maybe we could have photographic
memory for everything
maybe there is no limit to our
intelligence if we really apply
ourselves and meditate enough
right and later occurred to me that this
is probably not the case
i do know uh many people that are much
much smarter than myself and know much
more than myself
but it's often at the expense of other
things so they it
means that they tend to have a much
narrower view on
on things and know these things much
much more deeply and
apply their attention to exclusively
these things and not to others
of course there are some people which
are way smarter than me across the board
and
i am totally in awe of them but still
it's just a shorter human brain
and this shorter human brain i still
don't know
how much compute we need and how much
ingenuity we need
to replicate the schrodiness of course
right so even though we can see the
limits of what it's doing
to get this to run it might be possible
that it's doable or something that you
can
as an average person already buy and put
into
your basement if you really want to so
something in the order of
say 20k of compute maybe that's possible
and i'm
optimistic enough to say that there is a
chance that this is the case
yeah attention i've had numerous
discussions with our mutual friend ben
gertzell about that
right and you know i think we both have
come to the view that
i think it will turn out to be what is
the appropriate level of representation
my home academic discipline is
evolutionary computing
and in evolutionary computing again and
again and again it turns out to be
what is the representation on whether a
technique will provide traction on a
problem and so if it turns out that the
actual right level of representation
is indeed the neuron then probably 20k
computers won't do it if it's symbolic
you know truly symbolic and the
old-fashioned ai sense then probably
you know ten computers call it five
thousand dollars worth
will be enough but as i suspect if it's
some hybrid between the two
and kind of messy and has some very low
level stuff and some very high
level stuff and some transducers between
them it may be on the order you know
isn't my best guess and
you know i think ben thinks my number is
high but he agrees that it's a plausible
ceiling
essentially the equivalent of a thousand
powerful
desktop computers so we're talking on
the order
of a million dollars of hardware today
if we got the right level of
representation at it and of course a
million dollars with the hardware is no
barrier
at all to produce something as valuable
as human level
artificial intelligence if we look at
a thing like for instance gpt two or
three the models that open ai
has recently been working on in
publishing and
what goes into these models is a
relatively
moderate cause that still will drive
academic researchers
sweat on on their forehead but it's
something like two digit
million dollars that go into training
these models
and they are trained on a few years of
almost a full take of the internet that
has been filtered down to
something that removes most of the most
obvious crap and then
if it's very basic the common crawl is a
large part of
what you will find in a text that's
written in a given year on the internet
and then uh it is able to go through
this enormous amount of text that is
like a very
very large library there's lots of
babbling inside
and extract the all the meaningful
correlations or a significant part of
the meaningful correlations from it
in relatively short time right it's a
task that
is way beyond what a large group of
researchers could do in their lifetime
and it's done in the course of a few
days or weeks
these computers and this is a tremendous
achievement that you can do right and if
you imagine you would have something
that is only
able to process these data at a human
level
across all modalities maybe you trans uh
mocrify the data so
you get the highest bandwidth possible
in a nervous system
that has a capacity similar to ours that
would be a tremendous achievement if
so much data could be processed and
extracted in such a short amount of time
and i don't mean that gpt 203 are
human-like for me the fascinating thing
is that they get so far
that you have this a relatively simple
algorithm you can produce
embeddings over text and as they've
recently shown images
that allow you to make continuations of
the text and the images
that are basically uh surviving a type
of turing test where the audience is
unable to tell better than chance
whether the text that they're looking at
has been written by a human
or whether the image that they're
looking at has been
uh generated by a photograph you though
it's a lower resolution image
yeah that is interesting i mean as you
say this is not the way humans do it at
all and
i had looked quite a bit at gpt2 i
haven't looked at gpt-3 yet
and i did some experiments etc and
wouldn't have fooled me for very long
but
apparently could fool some people but
it's essentially
you know an extraordinarily deep pattern
matching system
and is that all human language
understanding is i don't know
it seems to me that there's something
missing in these brute force
deep learning approaches when it comes
particularly the language that yes it's
amazing what they'll do you know
the translation algorithms that google
famously developed
gpt2 and presumably gpt3 and gbt4
someday
you know may well be able to fool us but
do they actually
understand language at the level of say
for instance
reading every paper and every textbook
in cognitive science
and actually then being able to make
some
inferences about what's missing in
cognitive science and what new
theories or experiments are needed i
mean that's the kind of thing a human
could do not very well yet but that's
what you know a professional cognitive
scientist does
could gpt-4 do that i don't think so
the thing is that gpt uh 2 and 3 are not
sentient apparently right so they have
no
model of a connected unified universe
onto which they match everything that
happens
in real time and they understand their
own role in it and so on
it's not that they're far from it it's
just that it's not part of their task
then they haven't been asked to do that
this model has not been trained to do
such a thing
and yet the capacity that this thing has
is
tremendous and there's a lot of people
will say oh this is not grounded and has
no connection to reality
uh the question is imagine that all you
would have
as access to the world is your own
imagination the only the mental space
in which you can produce mental
simulations and lots and lots of books
and a way to parse them and at some
point you basically try to
hash out the space of possibilities in
which all these symbols that you're
confronting
can possibly make sense and give rise to
a universe that contains you
is this something where you can prove
our priority that this is impossible
that something like gpt tours is three a
simple text processor
cannot hash it out based uh just on the
finding one of the possible orders in
the patterns after notice there are not
that many
and once it figured out the relationship
between concepts in some kind of
relational space that is dynamic and
produces an evolving world can they
start parsing the wikipedia articles on
physics and all the papers on physics
that they read and understand
possible solutions to the big puzzles in
physics and so on
that allow us how to understand the
automata from which our world is
generated
i don't know that gpt 3 is seems to be
an incremental extension
over uh gpd2 so basically uses
magnitudes more data and
the learning curves are not bending yet
so it seems that you you can
extend this even further and the quality
of text that gpt
3 is producing in terms of coherence so
the illusion that this what it writes
corresponds to a self-coherent universe
where concepts are consistent for at
least the duration of the story
this is much much better than gpt2 so in
gpt2 you could easily see
when its construction fell apart then
lost coherence
and this is when the story becomes
unbelievable right you are
willing to entertain a completely
fictional story about a completely
fictional universe
as long as it refers to a coherent
universe
it might be a fantastic universe one
that doesn't make sense but it's one
that
works by certain rules like if you take
buffy the vampire slayer is a fictional
universe it's a
universe where everything is normal for
a sanitized version of normal it's a
suburbia that doesn't really exist
because it's so
perfect and stereotypical and the only
thing that's different from this
perfect and normal and stereotypical
world is that every year 20
of the population dies because of an
invasion of vampires
and everybody goes on with their life
and this
is is probably not realistic right we
know what happens if one percent of the
population dies in every given year
because to covet everything comes to a
halt
and so this is a universe that is only
meant
to highlight things in the stereotypes
and the normal interactions by
introducing this new element
and deliberately leaving everything else
that would be downstream from this
unchanged
and uh this is an interesting
construction that our mind can make it's
producing a universe that is derived
from our standard universe with all the
right constraints
and it's referring to this global
meaning and that it liberally
only changes very few things by leaving
the rest alone and
the people who understand this
understand these layers of meaning that
exist
and this would be an interesting
benchmark to see how many layers of
meaning can
gpt 3 distinguish between construct
versus gpt2
uh with respect to the complexity of a
brain
uh i think it's possible that the unit
is not the new one
but that it's the column it might be
that this is a simplification and the
actual units are somewhat orthogonal to
both neurons and columns
so in some sense you have units that are
made from
columns you have some that are made from
multiple columns and a couple neurons
and you have some where the neuron and
the couple neuro column and a couple
neurons interact in a specific way
or you could have processes inside of
the new one that play an important role
that you need to understand in order to
model the behavior of that thing it's
similar to
understanding the role of people in
society but there
at a certain level of granularity you
don't have people you just have
organizations
and yet to understand the interplay of
the organization sometimes you need to
look at individual people that play the
role historical developments
and uh to understand the behavior of
these people sometimes you need to look
into
very particular things in their own mind
that happened in a certain
moment in history and without that you
cannot understand it so this
simple granularity that that we put on
on the model
it's often too coarse to to make it
happen but if we
just entertain the idea that columns
might be the thing because there are
somewhat ubiquitous over the neocortex
they are interchangeable you can
basically cut out
non-specialized columns from the brain
of an
infant mouse and transplant them to
another area of the brain and
in their take they will adapt to
fulfilling the role of that part of the
cortex
so the columns seem to be pretty general
as far as we know right now
and column is something like 300 to 400
neurons
so we end up with uh something like in
the order of 100 million units and if
you imagine we have give or take 50
brain areas
it would mean that each of these brain
areas has in the order of a million
units
and the units can do way more than an
individual neuron can do even an
individual neuron would probably need a
three-layer network to
model it as a persopron but eventually
what they do is that each of them can
link up
potentially with a few thousand other
units
and these few thousand other units are
not what they're linked up permanently
it's the address space
it's what they can talk to and each of
them has a number of states that they
can have and dynamics that they can
undergo
set of functions they can model and it's
limited what they can do
right and so if you imagine that you
could
understand that each column is something
like an adaptive agent that is
doing local reinforcement learning by
some policy
and there's wired up into a global
architecture with the others
then maybe this does fit on a few larger
gpus already in real time
yep that could be now i want to clarify
something that i in my readings in your
book
and your talks and papers you talk about
100 million
columns as i recall from my reading i
actually did look it up this afternoon
there's probably more like 100 million
mini columns
and a million columns columns seem to be
made from multiple mini columns
which ones are you talking about when
you're i was talking about melee columns
and the formation of columns is also
different in different brains so for
instance if you look at a mouse brain
you will find that a large part of the
neocortex
seems to model the activity of whiskers
okay yeah make sense
and uh so the input space of whiskers
and uh
the columns form together into macro
columns in a way which are
almost like regions and
the it's not like you could look in the
brain you see very clear-cut
cells that are uh it's just that you
have groups of neurons that have more
interconnectivity
among each other and you lump them
together in a column and you also find
that they coincide usually with the glia
cell around which they're formed
but it's it's not by any means a very
very clear-cut architecture and seems to
be possible that neighboring columns
that
fuse and perform functions together and
so on under certain circumstances so
it's a lot more messy i think when we
look into this in detail
so you look at the mini column as the
closest thing to a
reasonably generic unit okay that's good
yes but it's really something very
i'm already squinting a lot and possibly
too much another thing that i wanted
to or put on my mental stack when you
mentioned it is the question
of whether we are just the least
intelligent
thing that is generally intelligent in
nature and
so i wonder is why there is nothing that
is obviously smarter than us in nature
because evil for a monkey it's hard to
have a brain that is larger than ours
there are brains in nature that are
larger than ours right whales have
larger brains elephants have larger
brains
why is it that whales and elephants are
not smarter than us because they
basically carry these brains around for
free right they have so large bodies
that they scaled up the brain with the
body size and it's not that they need a
proportionally larger cortex
to control a proportionally larger
muscle this is true for the body map but
only a very small part of the brain is
your somatosensory cortex
so what do they do with all this extra
capacity
why is it that they are not that smart
and
i suspect that if you make a system too
smart
it's very hard to control it it could be
that elephants have
uh massive autism because if they uh the
non-autistic elephants meditated
themselves out of existence
they basically started to understand
their role in the universe like
very smart monks and then as a result
they decided that uh doing
office politics all day and having kids
and participating in society
is just not cutting it and instead they
just go to do something more interesting
with their lives like meditating
and these elephants didn't have a lot of
offspring who knows that is the question
so i wonder
if this is a crazy idea i like that
it is a very crazy idea that's weird
that's i like that i'm going to lay that
one on somebody and say
oh yeah we only have autistic elephants
because elephants would otherwise be so
smart that they would you know be too
busy philosophizing to reproduce
i mean with the dolphins it's obviously
it's slightly different that dolphins
they live under water and you cannot
really hold a pen
underwater because everything you write
down will be washed out
so there will be no uh life for
intellectuals
because they cannot read it right
underwater so the
dolphins all only talk about sports and
celebrities and sex
and their society is not moving anywhere
and they have three dimensions too
that's another thing you know it
requires
a better brain to operate in three
dimensions at the speeds they operate at
right
but navigation is so much easier right
because you don't have to
solve all these not puzzles you can just
move where you want to
yeah and there's collisions are much
less likely right when you're stuck in
two dimensions collisions are constantly
undermined three dimensions it's easier
to dodge
right yes you'll probably also notice
that self-driving airplanes are
completely common
and standard for many many decades now
while self-driving cars are
difficult yep that's a good point
because the navigation that you need to
do on the ground to coordinate with all
the other things that are limited to two
dimensions
and have so many crossing paths are just
harder yep i love that
yes or geometry and cognition come
together and that's exactly the right
answer
let's jump back a little bit to a point
you passed over rapidly
but i would love to dig into a little
bit which is your statement that
in your belief the philosophical
questions
are sufficiently answered to to proceed
what is your take on the nature of the
mind
are you a strict materialist i suspect
that there is a misunderstanding with
respect to what
matter means i found that a lot of
people
think that matter is immediately given
somehow that we
have seen atoms and touch them and the
molecules and
the earth on which we stand and the
earth of which we move
and while this is experimentally the
case for the earth and the air
it's not so quite true for the atoms and
the underlying structure right
and when we look at this in more detail
it just turns out that what we mean by
matter
is a way to talk about information
and what we specifically talk about is
the way that we can measure change and
we notice that we can measure changes
periodic changes in place which we call
matter
and we can see how these periodic
changes in place move between places
across locations and this is what we
call momentum and the decryption of the
universe in terms of matter and momentum
is what we call physics right so physics
is the set
of functions that describes how adjacent
states of
the universe are correlated and the
idea of physics is that we explore the
hypothesis that there is a course of the
closed
lowest layer and the whole thing this is
what foundational physics is about
what's the close
causally closed lowest layer that
describes this entire
universe that we are in and this
hypothesis is that this layer exists and
it's discoverable to a large degree and
can be described or inferred is a very
successful hypothesis
and this hypothesis doesn't have a
really good contender there is not
another game in town that is quite
plausible
and what would that other game look like
and typically we
confronted with the notion of idealism
so instead of
matter being primary and matter being
the way information travels
in something like a mathematical space
so set of discernible locations
and trajectories that the information
can take between those locations
we think that the mind is possibly
primary so the conscious experience is
primary and subjectively that's true
right
consciously experience is uh affecting
and now
that we have given here in this moment
and this now is not the same thing as
any particular physical now
the physical universe is smeared out and
uncertain
with respect to that it has a very vague
and weird relationship to this
experiential noun that is
immediately given and if we make the
step to say that this experiential now
is everything where
something can be real an experience is
real by any observer
in the physical universe there's nothing
out there that can experience something
that can
be confronted with a reality because in
physics there's just automata
only unfeeling mechanisms everything
that is real
is in a dream it's in here with us in
this thing that we perceive that as
colors and sounds and
feelings and so on right so
if we make that thing primary there
still needs to be an outside that dreams
us
what is the thing that dreams us that
produces the dream that you're part of
the dream in which physics takes place
from our perspective and which
where we construct our ideas of physics
and everything else
and that thing out there this outside
world that we cannot access
this is still physics if we are dreamt
by a mind
on a higher plane of existence then it
turns out that this higher plane of
existence
is still the skull of a primate with a
brain inside of it
and that a higher plane of existence can
be modeled with the ideas of physics
it's not changing anything
yeah but is that necessary or when we
talk about let's say
human minds emerging from brains you
know i
you know i'm i'm kind of a naive realist
myself maybe i'm too naive but
i think you know there is a physics out
there and physics
emerges to chemistry and chemistry is
very
stable and predictable and from
chemistry we get biochemistry and from
biochemistry we get
biology and from biology we eventually
get neurons and then neurons we
eventually get nervous systems
eventually
we get brains and at some point probably
around the time of the reptiles or maybe
the amphibians we finally got
mind which is the subjective state
then mind is a new subjective state
that is packaged within physics i think
that's the alternative way of looking at
it
i suspect that you don't need to uh tell
the story from this direction you can
spend
hundreds of years sitting in your
monasteries in
tibet or whatever and be super smart and
have all the time in the world of your
hands because you convince the local
peasantry to give you free breakfast
every morning
because you're a holy man you sit
together with other other smart holy men
and you write books and discuss
psychology
introspectively at the level that
western psychology still
doesn't quite master and you do
understand many parts of the mind and
how they interact and so on
and you never ever venture out to
describe physics for some reason right
it's not necessary to do so
because you do not intend to
revolutionize society
and invent new means of production make
everything more efficient because that
would probably destabilize society
so you leave that as it is and society
outside is something like a periodic
process that you try to organize as well
as you can so it's
somewhat stable but you don't want to
turn it into a runaway pro
processes technological progress so why
would you want to look into physics
you don't need to do that right so many
cultures only focused on this mental
perspective
and the inner structure of perception
first
and uh not at the outer structure that
enables it
but if you're not looking into physics
from our perspective you are leaving
money on the table if you ignore
this entire scope of models that work
out that do
have predictive power tremendous
predictive power they allow you to build
machinery
that all these other civilizations could
not build and even think and reason
about and
did not even start to consider possible
because it was nothing that they waste
any ideas on what you can do in the
mechanical universe
it's it's possible to do that to leave
all that on the table
and our culture is a little bit weird
because our civilization is not that old
i think it just started 400 years ago
and we are mostly unaware of that
civilization break that we had when we
got out of the carts and the catholic
civilization is one that
obfuscated the area of the mind because
it made it all part of a mythology
so you didn't have the free space to
reason about psychology
within the catholic society all this was
taken up
by god's interfering with the selves on
the same brain
people were in some sense discouraged to
study psychology because it might
interfere with religion
and the physics that they engage with in
was also somewhat crude because access
to rationality needed to use
certificates that you would not
accidentally disprove religion interfere
with it
because it was in some sense an
anti-rationalist system that people had
to live in
and what we did was we freed our
rationality
for the first time in thousands of years
and this new rational society that woke
up with the enlightenment
dismissed all the stories about the mind
that the christians had ever told them
and thought of them as superstition so
we last lost many concepts and we are
still in the process of restoring them
for instance i'm fond of saying that
spirit is a word that we have dismissed
now as superstitious and
it's an old word that just means
operating system for an
autonomous robot and when the word was
coined it just
meant that the autonomous robots that
existed
so there were people there were plants
animals
cities nation states even possibly
ecosystems
but this was it there were no robots
that people had built
and now that we have autonomous robots
and they have operating systems
we understand that there is something
like an operating system and that humans
must have one too and
plants must have one as well and
obviously societies and civilizations
have some kind of operating system right
and we understand that this operating
system of society is
is not real it's virtual it exists over
the
coherent interactions of individuals in
the society in the same sense as the
mind
does not exist as a physical thing it
exists over the coherent interactions
of the neurons or whatever are the
constituting parts
are yeah well i think that's a very
important distinction and you know in my
study of complexity science
the way i will often say that is
reductionist science you know
let's call it old-style science is about
the dancers
while complexity perspective is about
the dance
and the dancers right so the things that
hold together let's say
a business company they're virtual
they're abstract
you know that you can't put your finger
on a particle and say this is
the operating system of a business and
yet the business is real
it is a series of coordinated actions
operating on signals with boundaries and
semi-permeable membranes
it has feedback loops i think that's key
and you make that point as well in some
of your writings that feedback loops
are absolutely critical in creating
higher levels of complexity and systems
at least they appear to be you know for
instance in one of my critiques of our
current operating system
is that our current society level
operating system is overly
driven around the money on money return
loop
you know everything is in the business
world and frankly in many many people's
personal world
is all about optimizing money on money
return
and that has produced many of the less
than desirable characteristics of our
era
but that is a real thing the flow of
money is a
information processing modality which
ends up coordinating
behavior of actual atoms and we'll get
down to the emergenciest's
argument about what is top down
causality but one could argue that
a society organized around money on
money return has
top down causality and that it requires
you know mary and joe to get up at seven
o'clock in the morning drive for an hour
and work in a job for eight
hours
and drive an hour home again so i think
this broader concept
of you know what is real to include you
know complex adaptive systems
gets around this false distinction
between dead matter
and live systems the notion of the
feedback loop is very old i suspect that
every
state craft that builds societies
deliberately had to have this notion of
feedback regulation in it
and understanding of nature i find this
already in
aristotle and in our intellectual
traditions
throughout the times this notion of the
feedback will be pointed in number three
where he describes that there must be
systems of competing springs in the mind
that
pull and push against each other and
keep it in some dynamic balance
and uh and so it's a very
classical notion and it became the core
of cybernetics and control theory
and it was a very popular paradigm for a
very long time
but i also suspect that there is a
little bit of traditional superstition
around the first and second generation
of dynamical systems theory
especially second order cybernetics in
the sense that we
attempted to think of these dynamical
systems as real
and i suspect that they are just models
they are not real
they are the behavior of too many parts
to count in the limit
when we describe how individual things
interact we can often track them and
see the low level processes that
change the evolution of one system
across the boundary
of uh by another and if you can no
longer do that because you're looking at
trillions of molecules for instance you
you will have to resort to models that
look at
the statistical dynamics of these too
many parts to count
and some of the resulting mathematics
have convergent results
and others have not and the geometry of
the world that we're looking at when we
look at dynamical systems this is
typically the stuff that is convergent
where we
can make models and so turns out that
newtonian mechanics is
these convergent dynamics of too many
parts to count within certain ranges
it's not real because you cannot really
make newtonian mechanics perfectly
working
from individual parts it's only within a
certain region of many many parts
too many parts to count that you get
something that looks a lot like
newtonian mechanics
and for a different region it's true for
einsteinian mechanics right
but these systems are not real it's just
a level of the modeling
that gives you coherence so when you are
an observer and you zoom into the
universe that contains you and the many
many parts that make up yourself
you basically will often find layers of
description
where you can make a coherent model and
these are the ones that we latch on as
description layers and then we discover
that they form a hierarchy
and then we try to establish causal
relationships between them
but these false relationships are not
causal relationships that exist in the
physical universe
personality is a model category it's a
property of the models that we are
making
so when we talk about these big
conundrums like the mind-body problem
you're not talking about how is one
physical set of things
like bodies connected to one other
possibly non-physical set of things
minds what we have to talk about is we
have here one category of model
that is our body map that is dynamically
arranged in space and articulated with
skeletal muscles
and on the other hand you have mental
states and mental processes and software
states and so on
and these two disparate categories of
models
how can we make them congruent well
they're actually they obviously
have to operate together you know i was
going to give an example
about what does reality and models
really mean
we talked earlier about companies right
that they're virtual
you can't really put your finger on
saying that's the company right it's a
standing wave essentially of action and
motion
but they're real in the sense that they
have traction in the physical world
and that's i think a reasonable
assessment of what is real
as an example think of a coal mining
company a company who digs coal out of
the ground
so in terms of traction in the real
world they dig holes
and they deliver coal to people who turn
it into energy so there are actual
things that are done in the world by
this virtual thing
called the coal mining company and
obviously trying to
track that at the level of atoms would
be ridiculous
and even tracking it at the level of
human beings would be exceedingly
difficult
and would maybe if you had billions of
dollars you could simulate a coal mining
company at the level of individual
humans
but interestingly at the level of
abstraction of accounting
it's quite simple right and people make
large bets
based on the future of one coal mining
company versus another
based on the signal very abstract very
high level of accounting information
that comes out
and the result is company a gets smaller
and company b
gets bigger based on people's
assessments of this high-level
information
and yet at the end of the day we have to
say that the mining company is real
because it is having very significant
impact on the real world well not
everything that has a significant impact
on the real world is real
in the in a particular sense right so
you could say that ideas have a
significant impact
on on the real world and it's very often
difficult to say what the idea actually
is because it only exists approximately
across
minds right so if you think about a
political movement
how would you say that the political
movement itself is real if the idea
behind the political movement is
understood by most people in different
ways but for a company it's much much
easier because we have a software uh our
legal system
that defines the conditions under which
a company exists
right and so you have a criterion by
which you can decide whether the company
is there or not
and what state it is in but this is
because we have created
a substrate for the company to run in
it's similar to what happens in our
computers we have a build a
deterministic system
with clear rules that allow us to decide
whether a bit is set in the gate or not
or in a register or not
and this allows us to construct
extremely precise models of the behavior
in the computer and pre-ordain the
behavior of the computer
it's a very specific thing that is
probably
different from mines where the state
that the mind is in
is still somewhat probabilistic yes
i would say that is true but it also
seems to be
at least in many cases in nature that
emergences to higher level
structural entities are built from
relatively well-defined lower level
units
and when you lack those more defined
lower level units it appears to be more
difficult to get emergent
properties to come into being so for
instance
you make the good point that the fact
that our laws
are relatively uniform and they result
in currency that has equal value
and that people can only be exploited so
far because of the limits of the law so
at some level they're
almost fungible may actually be part of
the mechanism that facilitates the
emergence
of the mining company perhaps in the
same way that
the fact that neurons while they of
course they vary
there's at least 100 different varieties
are not
that different compared to non-neurons
right they are
relatively fungible units of
construction
and they give evolution something to
work with to produce
higher level emergencies in this case
mind
and we take mind to be not just human
minds but minds all the way down
to wherever minds first come into being
on our evolutionary tree
and so i think that's interesting an
important thought that
we typically have a level of emergence
that has relative simplicity at the
outer
envelope of the component pieces at that
level and that those combining
allow us to reach the next level of
emergence
but we also know that the rules that are
implemented in the world that are so
uniform and so on for instance the
financial system needs to be in order to
work to be implemented in a way that is
rather uniform
you don't have large opportunities for
arbitrage right
where they have leaky abstractions and
yet we both know people that got
extremely wealthy by specifically
looking for the fine print
absolutely and not of these no systems
are perfect right biology
is subject to attack by viruses for
instance right a virus is not actually a
biological entity
it's essentially a flaw in biological
systems
that they're exploited by dead chemistry
in the same sense that
arbitrage yours are essentially like a
virus operating on
business looking for the flaws in the
system and there will always be them
so the two interesting questions one is
how much fine print is there in the mind
so
in to which degree does the mind not
emerge over the activity of neurons for
instance to which degree is this
simplification and uh to which do we is
it a very good abstraction and should
guide all of our thinking and not and
there are some people which
uh feel that the neurons are not the
right description at all and might have
even superstition connected to that
but i think it's still worth keeping
that in the back of the mind so that
there is usually some degree of
fine print involved when we make such
models and circumstances
under which this is not the entire truth
and more interesting things are going on
with respect to viruses right the
coronavirus is not a life form it's more
like a text
that the cell cannot help itself not to
read
and when the cell reads this text it's
doomed because it cannot
sandbox the idea that is contained in
the text it will have to turn it into an
action
and these viruses exist also in society
in a way right
but it's not as if the cell or the
biological life
ever existed for a long time at least
without these viruses
these viruses have been around briefly
after cells came into being probably so
the cells already contain a lot of
viruses the all the existing cells are
the result of many many interactions
that they had with viruses many of which
permanently migrated into the cells that
later on divided and became
us right so the same thing is true for
societies a lot of the ideas that we
have
are the result of the interaction with
viruses
that interacted with the pure
host ideas that had been formed in a
natural convergence rather than
being an infection process that
interacted with the natural convergence
state of a virgin mind
and then took roots in there and formed
an immune system to make sure that
competing ideas don't
take root in the same mind and so on
exactly i've often used the term memetic
viruses
for you know radical ideas that
challenge the status quo
you know for instance the scientific
revolution of you know starting around
and probably reaching its pinnacle at
least with respect to
the christian thing that came before
with darwin
were some very virulent memetic viruses
that were brought out by individual
thinkers and collectives of thinkers
and they put a substantial hit on
the pre-existing status quo model the
universe so i think you know
that concept of virus more broadly
constrained makes a lot of sense
there's of course the question whether
the virus increases the fitness
of the individual in the group and it
seems to be quite obvious that if you
look at society that the
uh viral evolution the memetic evolution
does not necessarily have to lead to
improvements nor does the
biological ones don't either right in
the long run i think that the things
that
don't work out are uh going to be uh
removed from the playing field this is
how evolution works
but it can be a temporary breakdown of
complexity that you observe so it could
be for instance that you
have a species that spreads over a very
large area of your ecosystem
and is very homogenous and this makes it
very susceptible to
an infection and then the entire
population gets or large part of the
population gets
wiped out by a relatively simple attack
vector
and if you have more diversity across
species you have more resilience
against viruses and the same thing can
happen in a society so
everybody is using the same kind of
social media and the same
news sources then society can have very
homogeneous virus infections
and as long as the virus is adaptive in
the sense that it makes the group
coordinate better
it can even convey an evolutionary
advantage on the group and make the
group out compete other groups
so i wonder to which degree we are the
result of such a viral domestication
process that
we basically are living in a
civilization that has
out-competed other civilizations because
people in it
they're very susceptible to this same
mind viruses
and as long as the viruses of
accompanied with some kind of church
and an immune system like an inquisition
that would make sure that everybody
would
be susceptible to the same viruses and
not rogue viruses
right the society is possibly more
successful than other societies
and then if you remove the church and
you have all these superstitious people
without
individual epistemology in any kind of
firewall against rogue ideas
that have no chance of being true when
seen uh edited with bright eyes
that this might create a dangerous
situation where your society just falls
apart because it splinters off into
random cults
yeah we're running that experiment right
now right possible
it's also possible that everybody just
suddenly seeing the light at the same
time right and
this amazing thing happens that after a
several thousand years of human
evolution we suddenly get to the point
where we have the right moral opinion
about everything that we didn't have in
the
1500s or in the 1800s or in
the 1950s or the 1970s or 1990s
now we see it of course everybody thinks
that they always think that they're
right every epoch thinks that they're
right but
i do think that one of the you know the
experiment that we're running of memetic
viruses everywhere
and eliminating many of the quality
control mechanisms that more autocratic
regimes have
may destroy us or may take us in a phase
change to the new level
and that's you know what some friends of
mine myself are working on is can we get
to a new level of civilization well
not all of our answers will be the right
ones but they'll be a lot more right
than the status quo in particular
learning how to operate within the
limits of our ecosystem
the current status quo seems to have no
breaks on it it does not know how to
stop
it keeps producing new things whether
they're actually good for us or not and
indeed many of them are dangerous to the
continued existence of the human race
think nuclear weapons
just finished reading this weekend a
very interesting book by
william perry and another fella
reminding us
there are still way too many nuclear
weapons out there and if there should be
just a mistake
it could knock us back to the stone age
quite easily right
let alone things like crispr or ai risk
etc which we'll talk about in a little
bit so
anyway that's interesting but let's move
back to our topic a little bit here
and let's go all the way back in time in
fact before modernism
really got started right at the cusp
with renee descartes and dualism
dualism seems to be a
strong attractor to this very day right
and a place against that a view of
talking about consciousness here
essentially or the mind or the spirit or
whatever we want to call it
descartes of course famously believed it
was of a different substance
than the body or energy or signals it
was
you know literally something very
unclear on how it interacted with
the physical universe but it was of
different substance
while someone like john searle who i
have found to be one of the more
interesting philosophers of
consciousness
argues that no consciousness or mind
more broadly
is nothing but an emergent system from
biology
very much like digestion and like
digestion it comes at a high energetic
and a high genetic cost to keep it going
and
you know those two seem to be the poles
of our historical thinking and yet the
cardian
dualism still seems with us i wonder to
which degree
uh the generation after descartes has
basically simplified his
thinking and that is especially apparent
when you look at occasionalism
the question of how the spheres interact
how is it possible that the mental
sphere
and the physical sphere can interact
when the physical sphere is causally
closed right it's if
the mental sphere doesn't need to be
causally closed it's possible that
something
is getting into your dream and messing
with it but how is the dream world
interacting with the physical world if
the physical world doesn't need any kind
of
external interaction to go with that and
there must be a reason why descartes
didn't see this as a very big problem
also what i find is when i read his
texts
he is often smarter than people give him
credit for
for instance in the meditations he will
interact with religion
in the same way as somebody saying
communism might interact with the
political dogma that is he will make a
nod to it
and pretend to see no reason to doubt it
and but will it defend it with this
implosively weave arguments
so that everybody who is able to uh
to get to the to a certain point in
their own thinking realize
this is not an argument that is good
enough to actually make a point
that this person is highly incentivized
to make then you only need to
make the next step and understand oh
maybe descartes was smart enough to
understand this
as well and smart enough to understand
that i would possibly be smart enough as
well to understand this
so we now we got this out of the way and
understand why he wrote it
right there is a reading of the card
that is relatively straightforward and
that is
that both substances are mental
substances in a way
so res extensor is the thing that for
instance jeff hawkins
numenta is so obsessed with this idea
that
everything that happens in the mind is
in some sense a representation
that maps to a certain region in the
same three-dimensional space
the same free space is here a model
right it's the
space that our mind models about the
universe
and this interpretation of jeff hawkins
is not complete because our mind also
has a lot of content that does not refer
to anything in the same moving free
space
so if you would say these two categories
of mental thought the physics engine
that our brain is generating to deal
with
predicting sensory data across all
modalities and all
modalities will be mapped on that
physics engine right everything that you
hear and see and touch is mapped onto
the same three space
and all the other things this would be
your skogi tens this is not res extensor
so just
say res extensor is the physics engine
that your mind is generating
whereas cognitives is everything else
and now you can easily see how they
interact
who's our software yeah i want to hop
back to a comment you made earlier about
the mind
not being causally closed do we know
that
is it possible the mind is causally
closed it's just very complex
the question is what kind of causation
you observe in the world and
this was an idea that first occurred to
me when i was
a kid and was playing on on telnet
there was a class of computer games
which were called nuts they still exist
in a way but most of them are now
graphical
multi-user dungeon adventures and many
of them were implemented in an
object-oriented language that allowed
you to create an arbitrary world from
text and this was very much like a text
adventure but it was a text adventure
that was dynamically evolving
and in which people could interact
across many computers so they would log
into the same server
and each of them would have a virtual
character and avatar
that would play in that world and some
of the people advanced to the point
where they would become wizards
and even gods and a wizard a magician is
somebody who has
right access to the rules of reality
somebody who cannot just use the surface
layer of reality that
is producing its a certain mechanical
structure
a certain substrate but you can go in
the substrate beneath that
and the substrate beneath that change
the rules by which everybody else has to
play
right this is what magic is about it's
also what magic is in a real world
about a which is somebody who focuses on
the way in which other people construct
reality
and messes directly with that layer so
the people around the witch
will have a reality that is open to the
attacks
by witchcraft by the right access to the
attention of people
to the way that people perceive their
own relationship to reality into the
bitch
there was the reason why the witches
have met the
similar fate under the expansion of
christianity as the jews did under the
expansion of fascism
it's basically a competing system of
seeing the world
that the dominant new vector did not
seem to be compatible with its own mode
so it tried to eradicate it so uh
witchcraft in these games existed right
it's a way to make people perceive
reality different by
changing rules by which people have to
perceive reality
and interact with it and uh this
witchcraft exists in our mind there are
ways in which we can perceive miracles
and make other people perceive miracles
it comes down to
creating a mental entity that you can
control in the mind of another person
that is changing the other person's
memories and perceptions
and as soon as you notice that you can
edit your own memories and you
catch yourself editing your own memories
uh you notice that the
interaction the causality in your mind
is symbolic there is stuff going on like
you uh perform a certain ritual that
involves maybe sacrificing a black cat
and as a result things in the real world
change
that are not obviously mechanically uh
connected to
the sacrifice of the black cat right
it's a completely symbolic interaction
the power of symbolic rituals can only
be explained i think by the fact that
our minds are not the course of the
closed doors layer
so you're saying that sacrificing the
black cat actually does
cause a change in physical reality no
it must cause a change in you the way
that you make sense of physical reality
in the way that which you relate to
physical reality
your the model that you make and the
actions that you perform as a result of
that change you regulate in a different
way and as a result reality will now
look different to you
that yes okay that certainly makes sense
so for instance you could make a ritual
to become
say a ceo of a company imagine you are a
a person that is an employee of
companies difficulty
to hold on to a job they are financially
struggling and so on they really don't
know what to do about this and
there is no way they can get out of this
they look into the
all the rules of reality that exists and
they can look into economic theory and
they realized i'm a member of the
working class
in fact there's nothing i can do about
this right and then they meet a magician
and the magician says
look we can do these rituals and a lot
of people that offer this magic as a
service
they have this abundance meditation and
expensive retreats and so on
and they basically reprogram you into
becoming a
say a glorified parasite or an
entrepreneur or an investor
and the difference between an investor
is not some magical ritual that has to
be performed at birth
or a change in the universe or a change
in the social order
it's a change in how you relate to the
world around you if you can
basically change your expectations in
such a way that you
consider yourself to be a very different
system you can often gravitate to a very
different place in society and in the
economic order
right and suddenly you have this big
house and this big car
and it's not that you are working
necessarily longer hours than you did
before but you just interact with the
outside world in a completely different
way
but you've updated your code i mean it
happens all the time and the same thing
happens say this relationship say you
want to find the perfect partner or
uh you want to meet very particular
people and you perform a certain ritual
and that suddenly changes the way you
interact with reality and
as downstream effects also makes other
people
interact with you in a different way and
suddenly you'll find yourself in a very
different position in the world
yep that's true but i'm not sure about
its significance if we assume that
something like a rough distinction
between hardware and software and i
understand
that there's actually many layers of
software in the mind
to update your code and then therefore
have a different degree of traction in
the world than you did before doesn't
strike me as particularly mysterious
you know if there is only one real layer
and it's the layer below quantum
mechanics
and everything above that is models
there is a lot of ways in which we can
meddle with these models to get the
outcome that we want
but so far we have not found any such
mechanisms to
actually impact the level of physics
all right we cannot change the mass of
electrons by a witchcraft we cannot
change
the spectral characteristics of alpha
centauri by
sacrificing a black cat exactly so there
seems to be
a level at which reality is causally
closed at which magic is not possible
this was the point that was trying to
make this hypothesis
that the world is entirely subject to
symbolical magic
falls apart at some point because there
seems to be a layer
outside of our minds that we cannot
change where the rules do not change
and the question between the
magicians between the people that think
that everything is a dream is
whether this is only because we have
agreed with each other that there are
certain parts of the dream are immutable
and we cannot defect from that dream
because then we will go insane
uh from the outside and from the inside
reality falls apart
just to sends it to chaos and of course
you cannot
disprove idealism right it's
unfortunately
in that area where could be true just
seems unlikely to me
and as i said i put my flag down many
years ago as a naive realist which is
there is a reality out there magic
doesn't work on physical reality
and it's not because we all agreed not
to change this because it's just a
different thing it's not a realm in
which magic can apply magic is a null
category
in the actual physical world in terms of
our
symbol space yes you can believe in
magic and you might actually think
about the world differently think about
people who go to casinos and believe in
luck for instance right and i know many
such
right and yet we all know that if you
look at games of true chance
with large enough n there ain't no luck
you know the house always wins and a
highly predictable amount in fact people
even done experiments i love this one
where they
track the win and loss records of a
group of nuns that went to a casino
and a group of ex-convicts that went to
a casino
and guess what they both won and lost at
exactly the same rates once n was large
enough
so you know these mine viruses that
attempt to claim that they can
manipulate the universe
but can't are a specific
example of what i might call malware
that the human brain is susceptible to
very very susceptible to just think of
the nonsense
that's loose in the world today about
covid19 for instance
but you know i do believe that we can
use a sharp enough knife
and say you know this is just not true
about reality
so uh the occultist might say to you jim
you've locked yourself into a reality in
which you will never win the lottery
because you
have made that commitment in the way
that you in which you constitute your
relationship to reality
that you can never beat the odds right
uh that magic is not possible
and it's hard to say whether that's true
for uh but when you compare the
hypothesis from the outside
you can basically see which one leads
into a consistent model of reality
you can of course always perform magic
imagine you run a company and everybody
in the company is depressed because the
numbers don't add up
and uh they are pointing towards doom
and then you hire a consultant and the
consultant performs magic
it changes the benchmark and suddenly
everything is awesome again
right so you pay the consultant
and now the question is what's happening
to your company
did the uh consultant oppose a better
model on your company by which it tracks
its performance in a better way
and uh regulates in a better way or did
they just cheat
and this is the issue with magic that a
lot of magic comes down to cheating of
course you can edit your memory and your
expectations and your interpretations of
what happens in between
but it might also change the way that
what you feel like for instance
even if you feel terribly you can just
imagine that you are
basically a king that presides over an
awesome kingdom
and that tomorrow is going to be awesome
again and this is just a very very short
intermission
that is does not actually mean anything
and this movement if you look at it from
this perspective is actually quite
bearable right
from this perspective you're probably
going to be a much happier person
but of course the question is in the
long run uh how well do you track
reality
yeah let's say for instance you decide
that i am the king of infinite space
and i decide i'm not gonna work and i'm
not going to do anything
and then i'll end up starving to death
right so at the end
reality bats last you know and i think
again in in terms of public affairs you
can claim
that covid19 is a hoax but that doesn't
stop the virus from doing its thing
yes of course you can also do the
opposite for instance
since my early use i think was early
teens when i
stumbled on the same thing as greta
toonberg did
which the limits to growth and
the environmental pollution that was you
know on a one-way trajectory
and the fact that we didn't have
regulation mechanisms implemented in our
civilization that could make it
sustainable before it breaks down
and that seemed to be an obvious thing
right that we are
instigating dynamics that when unchecked
will lead to the demise of our
civilization
and our main defense against that is
visual thinking
and once you realize that you get
depressed right it's terrifying
and the same thing is also true when you
look at society you mostly
focus on the things that get worse where
institutions gets understand where
people defect from what they should be
doing and all levels of
responsibility and everything is
constantly breaking down and getting
worse and this was my dominant
perspective for most of my life and i
must say the world didn't disappoint
right there was always enough evidence
to support this worldview so i
i spent my life being extremely worried
i did the inverse to the
king that thinks that what you see today
is just a short intermission
of slightly unpleasant things happening
in a life that is overall totally
glorious
i basically perceive the world as
something that is pretty much miserable
where the past and the future are
miserable
and the present is quite bearable but
this is
an exception that will surely be
corrected in the near future
right and this is an opposite distortion
that is unhealthy i think
though on the other hand i think your
analysis is approximately true as we
talked about before
that the current status quo seems to be
in a runaway state where it is going to
run over off a club
it totally is right 2020 is not an
aberration it's exactly the future that
we always expected would
start to manifest around 2020. and it's
starting and
and it'll get worse until we do
something about it but we could have
enjoyed the time in between so much more
that is true all right well that's this
is interesting this is interesting but
it's not quite on the main line of the
topics i wanted to go through but it was
very
interesting let's move back a little bit
more to
some of the specifics of cognitive
architectures
you know the nature of cognitive
processing
and particularly i'd love to talk a
little bit about what your views are
on the gap between humans and other
animals you know you alluded to the fact
that you know elephants have much bigger
brains than we do
whales do too some dolphins killer
whales i think but
we don't see you know elephants sitting
around philosophizing
and of course one of the theories and
probably the leading theory
is the difference is that somewhere
along the line we added a new class
of object into our brains something like
symbols maybe or language of
thought or perhaps it was a more
powerful form of procedural memory that
allowed us for instance to
conceptualize multi-part tools maybe
that was accepted for language but
something in that space
what are your thoughts from examining ai
and cognitive science about this
only one percent one and a half percent
difference in genes between us and a
chimp and yet
seemingly a giant gap in terms of our
cognitive ability
so there is an experiment that would be
very interesting to make and this is
how smart can dogs be there are
obviously extreme differences
in the intelligence of dog breeds right
and typically the small dogs that we
would like to have in our home tend to
be quite dumb
and the dogs that we use to
hurt our sheep tend to be very smart but
they are
the drugs that hurt our sheep tend to be
less controllable and they are less
suitable
as uh to keep around because you need to
negotiate the relationship to them
at a more fundamental level they're
somewhat less domesticated
and harder to domesticate and homo
sapiens
also seems to be a domesticated woman in
it i
sometimes wonder whether the
neanderthals were individually smarter
than us
but they didn't have scalable tribes
that that would scale into
states into societies with unknown
numbers of individuals beyond the dunbar
number
and in order to get people to cooperate
at scale you need to domesticate them in
such a way that you would selectively
dump them
down to dump down the epistemology so
they are able to
believe the same thing without proof and
walk on dog step
it's interesting though i will point out
that the confrontation between homo
sapiens sapiens and neanderthal
happened when we were still operating
below the dunbar number
you know that was obviously in our
forager stage you know at the latest 36
000 years ago so i'm not sure i buy it
with respect to
neanderthal on the other hand it's a
fact that archaeologists tell me is true
that if you compare modern man to
cro-magnon man say 12 000 years ago at
the very end of our forager days
cro-magnon man's brain was 10 larger
than ours
exactly so uh what i wonder is if the
evolutionary advantage that allowed us
to displace the neanderthals
to genocide them which is probably what
happened
was coordination it seems reasonable
cooperation is the human superpower
yes and it's not just the way we
cooperate in the sense that we make a
choice
individually to cooperate with somebody
else which what cooperation is usually
about
it's that we do this without thinking
that we do this automatically
that's interesting but again we're
really interested in the line between
let's say humans and chimps
right which is much bigger than between
cro-magnon and neanderthal neanderthal
and chimps is gigantic
too just a little bit smaller perhaps
yes
so the main issue seems to be lengths of
childhood i suspect
the length of our childhood is not too
much given by social circumstances
it does play a role but the main issue
seems to be the mat speed of the
maturation of the brain
and uh what you see is that in ancestral
societies it takes at least 15 years
before you are able to forage more than
you can eat
and in our society this period is even
longer
right so uh the time by which a kid can
basically earn more than it needs
uh in terms of upkeep is typically
longer than 18 in our society
so it's a very expensive period to
maintain in which you
are mostly doing exploration instead of
exploitation
and what we notice that in this period
it's not just a decision that the
individual is making to focus more on
exploration
the individual is in some sense
literally insane it
has an incomplete model of reality it
has an incomplete architecture
and i don't think this is just not
because it has not learned enough yet
but it's like the capstones are missing
it's like the training happens layer by
layer
and the infant spends a longer time than
cat infant
to learn basic special relationships and
learn contrast
and object permanence and so on and then
spends a longer time on
engaging with social relationships and
so on so you'll find
that a cat a house cat can have a better
model of the social reality and the
family and the
capabilities and relationships of the
individuals between them and then a
two-year-old baby will have
right and that's uh despite the baby
obviously being in some sense much
smarter when it comes to
spatial reasoning and so on even at that
age and definitely in terms of using
language
because most two-year-olds do have some
kind of language that far surprises
what a cat can do and so it seems to me
that uh
our ability might be conjunction of
slightly larger brain and optimized
architecture
but mostly more training data per day
when we bootstrap our brains
so we can make better abstractions and
that would be a very simple genetic
switch
so you could have a genetic switch that
basically
delays childhood every phase of it makes
it slower
and as a result gives you smarter terms
at the expense of longer childhood which
means that
gyms need to have much better
environmental circumstances
and more benefit from exploiting these
circumstances especially
so i suspect that moving into temperate
zones where you have a benefit from
planning ahead so you
can make agriculture and decide that if
you put stuff in the ground now it might
sprout
and if you keep a certain fraction of
the stuff that you
will not eat as seedlings for the next
year or
for years in which you have less
vegetation coming
all these planning ahead and so on is
going to give huge benefit
to a long childhood it allows you to
generalize over a very very
time spans interesting and then of
course humans
of course this is just one of these just
so stories about evolution so it may not
be true but
you know one of the theories is that
once we started standing on two feet
bipedalism
it produced evolution that constricted
the opening of the pelvis
that limited the size of the head of the
human baby
and hence while there was seemingly
something going on with rapidly
increasing brain size when our brains
are almost three times the size of a
chimp brain
even though we have similar body size
we're a little bigger body size but not
anywhere close to 3x
the constraint was the pelvis
arrangement
in the bipedal method of getting around
and hence
the evolutionary adaptation was to be
delivered very very very prematurely so
that we required a much longer time
to fully develop our brains unlike
actually the model animal i use in my
cognitive science work is a deer
white-tailed deer
and white-tailed deer is fairly
competent two hours after it's born
right it can get up it can walk around
it can find its mother it can flee from
prey
not very well but at least a little bit
compared to a two hour old baby can't do
a damn thing right
because the deer pelvis allows a much
larger
baby relative to the size of the mother
and
they have not been under evolutionary
pressure for really large brains either
so maybe that is the causal factor
of this very long learning process which
is interesting
the very interesting point you make
about however we got there the fact that
we have a very long maturity period
would tell us that we have more training
cases to run more layers to build and
more abstractions
and that's interesting having a large
brain is super nice i also
see some people that are obviously super
smart like say john dared and stephen
warfram it also have extraordinary large
scales
so it seems to be possible to have a
little bit more levee in the human
pelvis
to get larger skulls out there and
sometimes it also has good results
we also find people that have brains
that are
similar to say a gorilla brain and these
people are not necessarily mentally
impaired in any way they can
hold down a job they often study at
university and
can be reasonably smart people right so
the
size of the brain is not absolutely
everything there is a
certain devay in which you can use it
and it's probably nice to have a brain
that scales up better
but i don't think that brain size by
itself is the deciding factor
what about the theory that symbols or
language per se
is the bright line yeah i wonder about
this that's a very tempting idea and it
seems to be that the ability to
do grammatical decomposition is
something that distinguishes
the ability of humans and other apes
right so for instance uh elephants see
don't seem to be able to
produce new images so you uh they can
learn to draw
and what they will apparently do is at
least on in the instances that i've seen
so far
they don't generalize they don't make a
portrait they don't capture a new scene
they will produce the same image stroke
by stroke again
and again they can learn to do this they
have extremely good motor control
but there is no obvious generalization
and observation going into the
thing that they draw it's not a symbolic
depiction the same way as we do it
and if you look at the gorillas that
have been
raised in environments that they were
exposed to human-like stimuli and
human-like familial structures and so on
they did get in many ways to be more
similar to humans
than many people thought possible but
they also didn't do the grammatical
decomposition so when
coco draws a dog it looks like uh
jackson pollock it's basically an
arrangement of colors that seem to be
related
to what she was looking at but you don't
see the decomposition of the dog into
limbs
and a torso and a head and the
arrangement of the parts in it this has
not been properly reproduced
it's tempting to think that the lack of
a chromatic decomposition
in visual scenes corresponds to the lack
of the ability of the
gorilla or the tendency to use
grammatical language
and it may be the grammatical language
because it's such a compression right if
we
don't have symbols we don't have
something like at least partially
recursive
language and we have to manipulate
images only
which is at least one argument about
what's in the brain
in the pre-human era the density and
ability to manipulate easily
images is way less than symbols symbols
are tiny
right the concept of dog even if i don't
have a word for it i don't have written
language
a conceptual dog is much smaller than
many many images of many many different
dogs and so having symbols
may just make the brain exponentially
more effective
as an interesting question also if there
is a continuum between human
intelligence and ape intelligence rather
than a sharp cutoff
what i've read it seems to be it's not
sharp
but there's a big big gulf right as you
say
you can teach coco to put together very
simple linear sentences
but nothing at all like a recursive
sentence
yes but of course there are human beings
with developmental deficits
that have a similar cognitive capacity
right so there are certain syndromes
where the brain does not
develop in the same way as it does for
the others
and the question is what exactly are the
differences are these all pathologies of
course there are
in some sense because our genetic code
is the same
for the most part and they're just local
changes in genetic code or environmental
conditions
that prevented development to the
specification
that we are normally evolved to and yet
if you look at the differences also
between human beings i noticed this as
a tutor in computer science that the
performance that
people achieve as programmers can often
be predicted very very early on
depending on the kind of abstractions
that they are making in the first few
hours when you
are confronting them with certain ideas
and there is basically a hierarchy of
concept that you could
see in computer science say from
variables
to loops to pointers to functions to
closures
each of these concepts basically
requires more and more inversion and
abstraction
more and more pointers that you need to
keep stable in the same representation
the more abstract these concepts become
the harder it is to teach them
yep that is very true i found that same
thing in my technology career i hired
oh i don't know a thousand software
developers perhaps
and i got to be very very good at it
right you know i'm a pretty damn good
programmer but i know many better ones
but i do have probably a better
theoretical basis
in computer science than most but i was
able to recognize
at a very high level by asking
relatively few questions
where they stood on this hierarchy of
understanding and the ability to grasp
increasingly abstract software
development concepts
and you're absolutely right an hour
conversation i could predict at about
80 or 90 percent level of confidence how
far this person would go in their career
and there's this thing that most of
these concepts can be taught it's just
the
uh the amount of time that it takes to
teach the concept
is very variable yep yep
and realistically you only have a budget
of education
period right you have and realistically
the individual also has
a few decades right so uh if you
are able to just learn five percent
better
than somebody else this is going to
compound
and so i'm totally envious when you look
at stephen warfram who understood things
at 22
that i understood in my 40s yep i
certainly
saw that my dealings with the people of
the santa fe institute you know in the
business world i was
almost always the smartest guy in the
room at the santa fe institute i am
almost always the dumbest guy in the
room or damn close right
yeah these are great rooms yeah those
are great rooms you know as i said
that's not quite true but in business i
was definitely in a 99th percentile
in the world of complexity science on a
good day i'd be the 25th percentile
and that is it is you know you learn so
much so fast but you also
come to appreciate that there are people
who just operate at a very different
level of abstraction than which i will
never be capable
of but that's okay yeah these people
make me very happy
i'm glad they exist i like them a lot
and frankly i've spent fair amount of my
effort making their life better right
so they can do their work let's now
switch a little bit let's get a little
move down some in the stack of
abstraction you know in
your writings particularly in the book
you talk a fair amount about
cognitive architectures as an approach
to
we talked about the very beginning
thinking about the brain through
software in ways that may help us
understand ourselves and by the way
maybe do practical things but at least
understand ourselves better could you
maybe tell for our audience a little bit
about what
cognitive architectures are in the sense
you know things like soar akdar
and the sci model and how they differ
from what we read about in the newspaper
all the time you know the machine
learning
deep neural network approaches cognitive
architectures are a tradition that
mostly originated in psychology within
people that were strongly influenced by
the ideas of fibernetics and ai
and then decided to get real about this
and try to get a look at the way our
mind is structured because our mind
obviously has a lot of structure
to identify the architecture of our mind
and then
identify the principles that would need
to be implemented
and i think that most people in the
field of ai
would agree that there are two
directions that we need
to look into one is the general
principles of learning and functional
approximation so
when confronted with data how do you
efficiently build a model
over the data that allows you to predict
future data and interact with it and
build control models and the other
question is
in which particular way is this
organized in the human mind to give rise
to the particular feats
that humans have like learning language
interacting socially interacting with
the environment and with their bodies
to reflect symbolically over their
perceptual
uh representations such as feelings and
so on
so to how to get these two perspectives
together
is is for me a very interesting and
challenging question
and most of the work that is being done
in machine learning is not looking at
architectures the architecture is
only instrumental to a certain task
which could be for instance
text completion so we think about how to
organize structure into layers and then
how to stack the right number of layers
together or maybe implement an algorithm
that automatically searches for the
right number of layers
but we can also see that the brain is
not organized into layers
it's organized into regions that have
very complex
interconnectivity right so it's much
more
uh like a city with a rich set of
different uh ways of transporting
information around in it right so there
is going to be some
street network that is low level where
you can reach your immediate
neighborhood
and then but it's quite pedestrian and
it takes longer for the signals to cross
large distances and then there are
long-range connections like a subway and
then there is some
general interconnection network that
goes by the thalamus and allows to
for information from basically all every
region in the neocortex to get to every
other
to route information around and so how
how that works is a very interesting
question to me
you could also look from the perspective
of
training a network in some layer by
layer and then
as soon as you introduce a new layer you
make this a function of the existing
layers
and once that thing is trained you
introduce recurrent links so the
predictions of a later layer in your
architecture
are going to inform the predictions of
the earlier layers and become inputs to
them
right so they become the context in
which the lower layer makes its next
prediction
and the result is the same so instead of
getting a
nicely titty hierarchy of things where
you have an input and an output and the
input is your sensible apparatus and
your output is the
highest layer of your attention it turns
out to be fully interconnected and going
everywhere backwards and forwards
and suddenly your visual cortex is not
the first stage of processing
it's just the area where you store the
saw the textures
and of course that seems to be how the
human mind is structured and you know
when i react to deep learning mostly
feed forward though they're
now adding some simple recursion i i
always ask myself what are they missing
by not having these feedback loops
i think that everybody is aware of the
fact that they want to have recurrences
right from the start
when you look at the original work for
instance by hinton and zanovsky and
declay on
boltzmann machines that you have already
a very very general form of a model that
understands that a model is a set of
parameters that constrain each other and
each constraint is a computable function
that says
if a parameter has this value the
influence that has on all the other
parameters in the model
and then you can say that the deviation
from these constraints is energy
and you minimize the energy so it's very
similar to a spin last model in physics
where you try to
minimize the global energy state of the
system and when you achieve that
the system converges to an
interpretation of reality
and in some sense theoretically this
works very well as a model it's
pretty close to optimal but it's
impossible to train it turns out because
the search space for these variables and
constraints between them is
so dramatically large it's basically not
trainable beyond a few
parameters and so um hinton introduced a
constraint on this he said that
instead of having all these natural
links between the parameters all these
hidden links
we only link them in a forward manner
and in between the parameters we don't
have links and what's called a
restricted boltzmann machine rbm
and of course suddenly this thing cannot
model many things anymore and
the solution to that was to string many
of these rbms together in a network
so each of them is individually
trainable even though it's limited
and overall it produces a behavior that
the individuals could not
and this eventually leads to our current
deep learning architectures by a few
steps
but it's not optimal right the search
space is too large
the too many model states the ideal
model should be able
to be so tight that every model states
corresponds to a
possible state and reality most neural
networks
have many magnitudes more possible model
states which gives rise to adversarial
examples and limits
uh generative creativity because most of
the states that the system can be in
will not correspond to a world state
right
so uh for me the uh thing that a lot of
people don't pay enough attention to is
what uh these this transformer model is
achieving
it seems to be a way to think about
embeddings into a space
of features in a more general way so it
gets back to this original notion
of the balsamic machine from a in a
different projection
from a different perspective but still
and it is
this notion of attention and
self-attention binds features together
across the dimensions into a
relational graph and this allows you for
instance to generate a text
in which a noun and a pronoun are
associated over a very large distance or
where the initial
part of the text mentions the person by
name that performs a scientific
experiment and the later part of the
text
just refers to this as the scientist
or the researcher and uses them as
synonyms and
understands in some sense or represents
that these all these
uh entities refer to the same concept in
the text
right this is something that was very
hard to achieve in previous neural
network
implementations of language and uh
it's striking that this doesn't only
work for text it also works for images
so you can train this on images
you repeated the first few lines of an
image and it's going to continue the
image
which implies that internally while
predicting the image it's building a
representation
during the prediction of the next thing
of the entire image
until the end right so that's a
tremendous achievement it seems to open
the door to embeddings in general
across all modalities what happens if
you are
not just modeling the perception of a
system like this but also its decisions
is there a difference between making a
decision and predicting your decision
it's probably the same thing just from a
different perspective right
there is still going to be some
differences in terms of
the way we predict reality because we do
not predict reality just from the past
we also predict reality from the
perspective of the future that we want
to have so we limit our search space
to certain results that we want to have
achieved in the end
and this is a thing that the way we
access
the gpt-2 class or transformer class of
models currently are not doing
but there's nothing that is inherent to
the way these models are constructed
it's just inherent to the way you're
currently using them
that's very very interesting about where
we may be able to go
in using transformer based architectures
to get back to
you know the ability to do things at
long range and you know the transformer
architecture is still a heck if you look
at it it's a
very simple idea of course a very smart
simple idea that is then scaled up to
see how far it can go there's not an
obvious limit but that we have hit yet
to how far it can go which is
in some sense terrifying because it's so
simple
and uh you immediately wonder uh what
are the
uh optimizations going to be that we
will
quite inevitably discover in the next
few years yep that'd be very interesting
we'll have to keep a look on it we're
getting
long on time here kind of gone over our
time limit but that's okay
i'd like to drill down a little further
into details into some of your own work
now let's maybe give it another 10
minutes if we can
and talk a little bit about the psy
theory
dietrich dorner is that the guy's name
who came up with it and you wrote the
very interesting book
on the topic and one thing i found
interesting about it was that it was
connectionist
but the elements in the connection
architecture while they all use the same
architecture
could be at varying levels of
abstraction from quite high to quite low
and you know the system self-organized
and higher alcohol all that stuff so
anyway if you could
explain how all that works dietrich
turner is a german psychologist
a cybernetician strongly influenced by
these ideas in the 1960s
for a while shared a desk in the hanzo
colleague
is stanislav lam who became a good
friend of his
and at some point their directions
diverged even though
they remained friends over the years
until them died and
then decided that the biggest influence
that he could have on the development of
artificial intelligence in cybernetics
would be to become a philosophical
science fiction author
because he would be free of the
constraints of academia and to actually
get things to work
and instead anchor ideas in the minds of
people that would have a larger
influence that
writing a few papers about systems that
he would not be able to get
to work in the next decade or two
decades
and uh donor was more optimistic he uh
thought that behavioral psychology which
was uh
all the rage at the time is not cutting
it and instead we need to do cybernetic
and computational
psychology and just implement a model of
how people work and then we'll be done
and uh he thought that he'd be done in
the late 1970s originally and told his
wife
that they would have an awesome time on
the beach after that because their job
would be finished we would have
computers that think and solve all our
problems for us and of course that
didn't quite work out but he
mostly on his own reinvented or invented
in parallel many of the ideas that ai
was into so he started out with
monolithic systems
that later became situated connected to
environment and then this environment
could be
changed by the system so it became an
agent architecture
and then he invented multi-agent
architectures and
all the while these architectures had
models of autonomous motivation in them
that were
based on this cybernetic idea of a
feedback loop that would regulate it all
and what i liked about his work was
that he was extremely serious about
building minds and
his heart seemed to be in the right spot
and also his ideas seem to be on the
right spot so
when there started reading his ideas in
the 1980s
uh most of the psychologists ignored him
because uh there was
theoretical psychology he uh for a long
time had the only chair
of theoretical psychology in germany
there was no such thing as theoretical
psychology
and uh that basically tried to bridge
between ai ideas and psychology while he
was mostly unaware
of the discourse that would take place
in ai and
uh you would read sometimes something
about it but always come up with his own
solutions
the first interview that i read with him
a very
consternated journalist of the german
magazine spiegel which is the equivalent
of the times
uh in us asked him why he would claim
that these systems are
have two emotions it would be wouldn't
everybody understand that it's
impossible for a computer to have
emotions
and turner replied very earnestly that
it really depends on your definition of
emotion and that if you have a
definition of emotion that doesn't have
an extension that you can understand you
probably don't know what you're talking
about
and then he went on to try to define
emotion and then ex try to explain
why his systems would have emotion in
this sense
and i i agreed with them and uh while i
thought that this notion of emotion does
not capture everything
that emotion captures for me when i
define emotion
uh it seemed to me that there is a
trajectory along which we can make this
definition richer and extend it and then
implement all these missing things
until we all agree so i i thought this
is probably the way to go
and i started reading all this stuff and
then
decided to systematize it and translate
into something that could be actually
implemented and
because there was less bold than him i
took his science theory style this
letter
that psychologists love to use and they
make a theory of everything
and translate it into mycocy my humble
attempt as a computer scientist to get
some of the concepts at least to work
and i spent uh almost a decade with that
and
this uh book principles of synthetic
intelligence is an attempt to
turn the site into an acronym for a book
title of course
and uh to systematize his work and make
it accessible to people in cognitive
science
and artificial intelligence so this is
what the first
third of the book is doing summarize
donors ideas
and systematize them contrast them with
ideas that were around in the field
compared to related work and then
the second part of the book is
implementing these ideas and the third
part of the book is
critiquing them and explaining where i
think we need to go beyond them
and this is a snapshot of my
understanding back then and my
thinking has since then in many areas
evolved a great deal and moved on it's
not that i
still think that these now think that
these are bad ideas it's just
this would be the first third of the
next book that i would write if i find
the time
okay interesting and what is the status
of the micro sci project i saw there was
a
micro sci 1 which ran only under windows
and then there was a microsite 2 that
was written in python
but i looked at the github project
looked like there hadn't been any
updates on it four or five years
is anybody working on it is it being
used at this point
yes so the the first microsoft we always
try to be platform independent because
the
people that i worked with they had macs
they had linux they had windows
and we wanted to make this accessible to
anyone so the first one was done in java
and was written directly as plugin to
the eclipse ide and it was using all the
typical things that you would use in
2003 so lots of xml
and lots of factories and i think that
back then
it was respectable software engineering
but it was very different from what we
would do five years later when
everything was going to be pyson
and you would put your ui in the browser
so uh the way to make platform
independent implementation of a research
cognitive architecture
was different when you did the second
edition and the second edition
was being used in two startups one went
defunct
i was in uh ai planning startup the
other one
was started later by students of mine
mostly i'm also a co-founder in this
it's called microsoft industries and
uses the microscope architecture
as a framework to implement control
networks for
industrial robots mostly and
also does a little bit of basic research
but most of the things that are done are
in-house so while we still
post the architecture for people that
want to use it and some people use it
and play around with it
the main evolution takes place within
the company for proprietary projects in
britain
and at the moment i am using
microsci internally for trying out
a certain models that i have about using
spreading activation networks to
produce procedural strips that interact
with cellular automata
representation and processing layers
also thinking about
uh what the next edition of microsite is
going to be and how it's going to be
implemented and we have some ideas about
this but it's too early to talk about
this
ah okay i was going to see if i could
get you to talk about what microsoft 3
might be looking like
i'm going to throw out some ideas which
i've also i'm always throwing at
ben gertzel about opencog which is i
hope when you do it that you think
big so many of these cognitive
architectures or
ai platforms were unfortunately
conceptualized to only run
on a single machine or a small cluster
and
one of the things that we now have is
really cheap computation and really fast
networks and if i were designing a
platform
for thinking machines i would look
carefully at some of the apache
large scale very big cluster very large
throughput
platforms like ignite and flink and
spark
it has two big advantages one that they
operate at massive scale
and secondly it gets the implementer out
of having to write a whole lot of
low-level
stuff and so you can leverage your
manpower
in the higher levels of the actual value
add rather than trying to optimize how
you move pointers and things of that
sort these guys have already figured
that out
exactly i also wonder whether we should
still think so much of
vision system and more across systems
so instead of thinking about how we can
make a
representation that is completely
homogenous think about how different
parts of the architecture
implement general principles that allow
them to learn how to interact with all
the other parts
and if that happens you can for instance
instead of reinventing linear algebra
on your gpu that then reinvents how to
render graphics on the gpu using linear
algebra
you can for instance use existing shader
programs and graphics engines
and learn how to use them instead i
think that's right and
again there is no free lunch so people
say oh yeah well you have ignite you
know a true
gigantic key value store well guess what
on distributed architectures there is no
free lunch
right queries that have to traverse the
network have very different costs than
ones that don't
and so having a system that can
self-organize to take advantage of the
realities of its network
is probably the real secret to maximize
these super powerful gigantic scalar
tools
but using them naively you can produce
degenerate queries quite simply that
yes you have 100 000 processors but
guess what it's still slow because the
data is all over the place that makes
any single query
inefficient so these things are by no
means panaceas but
if i were going to go down that road i
would be thinking of these very large
scale
data processing architectures rather
than writing something to run on a
single machine or a small cluster
well this has been a very interesting
conversation
we went a little bit longer than i was
thinking we didn't get to some of the
topics i had on my list but that's okay
i think our people will find this to be
a quite interesting deep
dive into the mind of yoshibak thank you
i really enjoyed our conversation
and i'm sure we have more topics left
for
future time thank you very much
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller